Register of the United Nations Conference on International Organization proceedings
Hoover Institution Archives
United Nations Conference on International Organization proceedings
1945
47026
Hoover Institution Archives
17 manuscript boxes, 4 oversize boxes, 1 envelope (9.8 linear feet)
Sound recordings of conference proceedings recorded by the National Broadcasting Company (NBC), photographs and contact sheets depicting delegates and scenes at the conference, and printed copies of the Charter of the United Nations. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
United Nations Conference on International Organization (1945: San Francisco, Calif.)
National Broadcasting Company, Inc.
Access
Boxes 3-6 closed. Use copies of the sound recordings in boxes 3-5 are available; box 6 contains broken discs.
Use copies of all sound recordings in this collection are available for immediate access; digital copies also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1947, with an increment received in 2017.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Related Materials
Sound Recordings from the NBC Radio Collection, Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division, Library of Congress
Charles Easton Rothwell papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Ivan S. Kerno papers, Hoover Institution Archives
J. Rafael Oreamuno interview, Hoover Institution Archives
Harold H. Fisher papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Charles F. Darlington papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Carter L. Burgess papers, Hoover Institution Archives
John Wesley Masland papers, Hoover Institution Archives
America's Town Meeting of the Air sound recording, Hoover Institution Archives
South Africa Delegation to the United Nations Conference on International Organization proposal, Hoover Institution Archives
Commonwealth Club of California records, Hoover Institution Archives
Preparatory Commission of the United Nations records, Hoover Institution Archives
Bruce T. Mitchell collection, Hoover Institution Archives
G. William Gahagan Papers, Hoover Institution Archives
United States Foreign Broadcast Intelligence Service miscellaneous records, Hoover Institution Archives
Historical Note
The United Nations Conference on International Organization was convened in San Francisco from April 25 to June 26, 1945. Fifty nations participated in the conference at the invitation of the four sponsoring governments, the United States, the United Kingdom, the USSR, and China. The four sponsors invited to the conference those nations that had entered into a state of war against one or more of the Axis powers and that adhered to the Declaration by United Nations of January 1, 1942. Forty-two nations accepted the invitation, and after the conference began, Argentina, Denmark, the Belarussian Soviet Socialist Republic, and the Ukrainian Soviet Socialist Republic were admitted. Poland was not present, but space on the Charter was reserved for the signature of a representative of Poland. The U.S. government paid the expenses of the conference, which were less than 2 million dollars.
More than 3,500 conference delegates and staff members assembled in San Francisco for the conference. Thirty hotels and three clubs provided housing and offices, while the Veterans Building and the Opera House were used for the conference's central activities. More than 2,500 representatives of the press, radio, and newsreels covered the conference.
The conference considered four areas, consisting of the Dumbarton Oaks plan, suggested amendments to the plan, a draft addition to the plan providing for a trusteeship system for dependent areas, and preliminary studies on the creation of an International Court of Justice.
The conference began with eight plenary sessions held in public. At these opening sessions, the chairmen of the delegations of the sponsoring powers, followed by the chairmen of the other delegations, addressed the conference. During this time the conference's organization and work plan were determined. The charter was divided into four sections for consideration by four commissions, which in turn divided the work among multiple technical committees. The commissions and technical committees began their assignments as the opening sessions wrapped up. As the technical committees completed their work they submitted reports to the commissions, which pulled them together into commission reports, which were submitted to the Coordination Committee, which prepared the text of the charter as a whole.
The Charter of the United Nations, together with the Statute of the International Court of Justice, was presented and adopted unanimously at the ninth plenary session on June 25, 1945. A signing ceremony was on June 26 and lasted all day. Afterwards a closing session was held, with speeches by the president of the United States, the chairmen of the delegations of the sponsoring powers, and chairmen of five other delegations--Brazil, Czechoslovakia, Mexico, Saudi Arabia, and South Africa--chosen to represent the diversity of nationalities and geographic areas. The charter entered into force, in accordance with its Article 110, paragraph 3, on October 24, 1945, following the deposit of the instruments of ratification of the five permanent members of the Security Council and a majority of all other signatories.
Five official languages--Chinese, English, French, Russian, and Spanish--were recognized at the conference, but only English and French were used as working languages and all documents were issued in both. More than one hundred people translated documents and interpreted discussions. Speeches made in English were interpreted into French and vice versa, and speeches in other languages were interpreted into English and French.
In terms of administrative organization, the Conference in Plenary Session was the highest authority at the conference. It was responsible for final votes and adopting the text of the charter. The senior members of the delegations of the four sponsoring governments presided in rotation over the plenary sessions.
Four general committees were established under the plenary level. In recognition of the host country, the conference asked the chairman of the U.S. delegation to chair the Steering and Executive Committees.
The Steering Committee considered major questions of policy and procedure and distributed work to the committees. The committee had fifty members, consisting of the chairman of each national delegation.
The Executive Committee was a smaller unit that made recommendations to the Steering Committee; it was composed of the chairmen of fourteen delegations. These fourteen represented the four sponsoring governments and the ten co-elected members.
The Coordination Committee assisted the Executive Committee and supervised the final drafting of the charter. It was composed of representatives of the fourteen delegations previously mentioned. An Advisory Committee of Jurists provided assistance to this committee.
The Credentials Committee verified the credentials of delegates and was composed of representatives from six delegations.
Below the committee level, four general commissions studied the main issues and coordinated the work of twelve technical committees. The technical committees drafted proposals and could designate subcommittees as needed. The leadership of the commissions and technical committees consisted of a chairman and a rapporteur; these positions were divided among all of the national delegations. The Steering Committee nominated delegates for these positions, with approval by the conference.
Commission I studied general provisions and managed the work of Technical Committee 1 (preamble, purposes and principles) and Technical Committee 2 (membership, amendment and secretariat).
Commission II focused on the general assembly. It coordinated the work of Technical Committee 1 (structure and procedures), Technical Committee 2 (political and security functions), Technical Committee 3 (economic and social cooperation) and Technical Committee 4 (trusteeship system).
Commission III considered the security council. It oversaw the work of Technical Committee 1 (structure and procedures), Technical Committee 2 (peaceful settlement), Technical Committee 3 (enforcement arrangements) and Technical Committee 4 (regional arrangements).
Commission IV studied judicial organization. Its committees were Technical Committee 1 (international court of justice) and Technical Committee 2 (legal problems).
A Secretariat provided general administration to the conference. It prepared agenda and working papers for discussion, compiled minutes and records of meetings, and provided the array of standard services required by any international conference.
More than five thousand documents were considered at the conference; the primary ones were published as Documents of the United Nations Conference on International Organization, San Francisco, Volumes I to XX, 1945-1954.
Scope and Content of Collection
The United Nations Conference on International Organization proceedings contain sound recordings of conference proceedings recorded by the National Broadcasting Company (NBC), photographs and contact sheets depicting delegates and scenes at the conference, and printed copies of the Charter of the United Nations.
The Subject File includes a packet of documents issued to conference attendees, a chart illustrating the proposed structure of the United Nations, a broadside copy of the United Nations Charter featuring replica signatures of the delegates, and a hardbound copy of the 1945 United Nations Charter with translations in French, Chinese, Russian, and Spanish.
The photographs and contact sheets are largely credited to Ralph Crane, Ralph McAvoy, and Peter Stackpole of Life Photo; one is credited to Green Park Studios of London. Scenes and persons depicted include: posed and candid portraits of delegates and conference attendees; the opening, plenary, and committee sessions; the signing of the UN Charter; The San Francisco War Memorial Opera House; Herbst Theatre; Union Square; and The Hoover Institution (visited by many of the delegates).
The sound recordings are instantaneous lacquer discs documenting conference proceedings, including plenary sessions, committee meetings, the arrival of President Truman, and the signing of the UN Charter. The Hoover Institution Archives digitized the discs in 2009-2010. Access copies of these recordings are available in the Hoover Archives Reading Room.
The Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division at the Library of Congress has a related set of NBC news radio broadcasts documenting the conference. The collections at Hoover and the Library of Congress are neither identical nor wholly individual. Instead, they overlap somewhat and complement each other, the materials at Hoover being recordings of actual conference proceedings, while the recordings at the Library of Congress contain more reporting and analysis by NBC News staff. Researchers interested in the Sound Recordings from the NBC Radio Collection at the Library of Congress can visit their Recorded Sound Reference Center website [http://www.loc.gov/rr/record/] for more information.
Scope and Content of Incremental Materials
Boxes 7-21 of the collection consist of material relating to the United Nations collected by M. Margaret Ball, a scholar of International Relations and a professor at Wellesley College. The incremental materials include United Nations Conference on International Organization (UNCIO) commission and committee documents, including draft reports (with comments), reports, recommendations, maps, letters, agendas, and meeting summaries, mostly dating from 1945. Also included are General Assembly, Security Council, and Economic and Social Council documents, as well as miscellaneous other documentation (booklets) collected by Ball, who was in attendance. The materials are mostly in English, though some documents are in French.
United Nations; Sound recordings.
- Subject File, 1945 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes a packet of documents issued to conference attendees, a chart illustrating the proposed structure of the United Nations, a broadside copy of the United Nations Charter, and a hardbound copy of the 1945 United Nations Charter with translations in French, Chinese, Russian, and Spanish.
  - "Charter of the United Nations and Salute of the International Court of Justice"
    Includes translations in French, Chinese, Russian, and Spanish.
  - Charter of the United Nations
    Broadside large-form presentation of the Charter. Includes replica signatures of delegates. Double-sided.
  - Chart of the United Nations as Proposed at Dumbarton Oaks
    Broadside chart published by the U.S. Department of State depicting relationships between the varying offices and departments within the United Nations.
- Photographs, 1945 (Box 2, Envelope mE)
  Photographic prints and contact sheets depicting conference attendees and scenes from the conference.
  - 21 photos and contact sheets (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - 13 photos and contact sheets (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - 11 photos and contact sheets (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - 16 photos and contact sheets (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - 18 photos and contact sheets (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - 21 photos and contact sheets (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - 17 photos and contact sheets (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - 16 photos and contact sheets (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - 12 photos and contact sheets (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - 15 photos and contact sheets (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - 16 photos and contact sheets (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Oversize photographs (Envelope mE)
- National Broadcasting Company Sound Recordings of Proceedings, 1945 (Boxes 3-6)
  Instantaneous disc recordings of NBC news coverage of the conference's plenary sessions, committee meetings, and the signing of the UN Charter. 146 sound lacquer discs. Boxes 3-6 closed; digital use copies of boxes 3-5 available.
  Note: The item titles in this series are taken from the labels on the discs themselves, presumably committed by NBC Radio at the time the discs were cut. Consequently, the dates included in each title reflect the dates the recordings were aired (or meant for air) and not the dates the respective conference sessions actually occurred.
  The Conference in Plenary Session was the highest authority at the conference. It was responsible for final votes and adopting the text of the charter. The senior members of the delegations of the four sponsoring governments presided in rotation over the plenary sessions.
  Commission I studied general provisions and managed the work of Technical Committee 1 (preamble, purposes and principles) and Technical Committee 2 (membership, amendment and secretariat).
  Commission II focused on the general assembly. It coordinated the work of Technical Committee 1 (structure and procedures), Technical Committee 2 (political and security functions), Technical Committee 3 (economic and social cooperation) and Technical Committee 4 (trusteeship system).
  Commission III considered the security council. It oversaw the work of Technical Committee 1 (structure and procedures), Technical Committee 2 (peaceful settlement), Technical Committee 3 (enforcement arrangements) and Technical Committee 4 (regional arrangements).
  Commission IV studied judicial organization. Its committees were Technical Committee 1 (international court of justice) and Technical Committee 2 (legal problems).
  - Opening session, 1945 April 25 (Box 3, tape cabinet)
    Presiding: Edward R Stettinius Jr.
    Speakers: United States President Harry S. Truman, California Governor Earl Warren, San Francisco Mayor Rodger D. Lapham, Secretary Stettinius.
    Part 1 is unavailable due to the source reel being broken.
  - First plenary session, 1945 April 26 (Box 3)
    Presiding: Edward R. Stettinius Jr.
    Speakers: Joaquin Fernandez y Fernandez of Chile, T. V. Soong of China, V. M. Molotov of the Soviet Union, and Anthony Eden of the United Kingdom.
  - Second plenary session, 1945 April 27 (Box 3)
    Speakers: Guillermo Belt Ramirez of Cuba, Francis M. Forde of Australia, Paul-Henri Spaak of Belgium, Victor Andrade of Bolivia, Pedro Leao Velloso of Brazil, and W. L. MacKenzie, King of Canada.
  - Third plenary session, 1945 April 28 (Box 3)
    Presiding: T. V. Soong of China.
    Speakers: Jan Masaryk of Czechoslovakia, Abdel Hamid Badawi Pasha of Egypt, Julian R. Caceres of Honduras, Sir A. Ramaswami Mudaliar of India, Mostafa Adl of Iran, Eelco N. Van Kleffens of the Netherlands, and the chairman of the delegation from Lebanon.
  - Fourth plenary session, 1945 April 28 (Box 3)
    Presiding: V. M. Molotov.
    Speakers: Hector David Castro of El Salvador, John Sofianopoulos of Greece, Carlos P. Romulo of the Philippines, and Jose Serrato of Uruguay.
    This recording includes a segment where the session is interrupted by (premature) news of Germany's surrender.
  - Fifth plenary session, 1945 April 30 (Boxes 3, 6)
    Concerns Argentina.
    Speakers: Joseph Bech, Guillermo Belt Ramirez, Jan Christian Smuts, Blatta Ephrem Tewelde Medhen, Georges Bidault, Guillermo Toriello, Gerard E. Lescot, Arshad Al-Omari, C. L. Simpson, and Hasan Saka.
    Part 11 is unavailable due to the source disc being cracked.
  - Sixth plenary session, 1945 May 1 (Box 4)
    Presiding: Edward R. Stettinius Jr, who often asks the conference to recognize wounded American soldiers visiting the conference.
    Joseph Bech reports on work of the credentials committee. Guillermo Belt Ramirez reports on the work of the steering committee. Jan Christian Smuts of South Africa speaks on the impact of war, outlines the need for international organization, and calls for the charter to be a declaration of human rights. Blatta Ephrem Tewelde Medhen of Ethiopia speaks on what is needed to preserve peace in the future. Georges Bidault speaks in French for about twenty minutes. Guillermo Toriello of Guatemala speaks about hopes for the United Nations, peace, and quality of life across the world. Gerard E. Lescot of Haiti speaks. Arshad Al-Omari speaks about Iraq's involvement in the war and its hopes for securing world peace. C. L. Simpson of Liberia offers support to nations that were conquered and liberated during the war and gives thanks to the liberating countries of the war before discussing the Security Council. Hasan Saka of Turkey speaks in French for about fifteen minutes.
  - Seventh plenary session, 1945 May 1 (Box 5)
    Presiding: T. V. Soong.
    Guillermo Belt Ramirez of Cuba speaks on the unification of the world, comparing the United Nations to the United States of America. He calls for complete democracy and equality among the nations within the body and advocates against permanent members in the Security Council.
    Joseph Bech of Luxembourg speaks in French.
    Peter Fraser of New Zealand eulogizes Franklin D. Roosevelt and hopes for world peace under the United Nations. He praises the work of the Allies during the war, both before and during active fighting. He notes that the Dumbarton Oaks proposal was not sacrosanct and is open for amendment. He worries the powers of the "great powers" will be too large, in effect making the smaller countries' opinions moot. He criticizes the veto power, saying an aggressor nation could use its veto power to cover itself from criticism. He also discusses trusteeship. He concludes calling for economic and social equality.
    Carracido Parra Perez speaks in French.
  - Eighth plenary session, 1945 May 2 (Box 5)
    Presiding: V. M. Molotov of the Soviet Union.
    Alger Hiss of the United States speaks about how the conference will proceed, Ezequiel Padilla of Mexico offers his ideal for future international relations and organization, Trygve Lie of Norway speaks about his country and what it hopes for in the organization, Mariano Arguello Vargas of Nicaragua speaks about Franklin D. Roosevelt and his impact on the United Nations, Roberto Jimenez of Panama speaks on the failures of the League of Nations and lists concepts he feels should be central to the organization, Manuel Gallagher of Peru speaks on how to avoid future wars, Faris El-Khouri of Syria speaks about the state of the world, Ivan Subasic of Yugoslavia recounts the experiences of his country during the war and its support of the idea of the United Nations to maintain peace.
  - Proceedings of Commission IV, Committees 1 and 2, 1945 May 19 (Box 5)
    On the international court of justice and other legal problems.
    Presiding: Carraciolo Parra Perez.
    Speakers: Manuel Gallagher, Nasarat Al-Farici, Abdel Hamid Badawi Pasha, Mariano Aguella Vargas, and Emanual Abraham.
  - Proceedings of Commission II, Committee 1, 1945 May 30 (Box 5)
    On structure and procedure of the general assembly.
    Presiding: Jan Christian Smuts.
    Speakers: Kusma B. Kisilev, a delegate from the Netherlands, Herbert Vere Evatt, V. M. Molotov, Victor de Laveleye, and K. V. Novikov.
  - Proceedings of Commission II, Committee 3, 1945 June 11 (Box 5)
    On the economic and social council.
    Speakers: G. Myrddin Evans speaks about how the recent past is important to thoughts about the council, a delegate from the Soviet Union expresses optimistic hope for the impact of the council, Bertha Lutz speaks about the role of women in the conference and gender equality, Miss Wu Yi-fang delivers a "post-script" to the comments of the Soviet delegate, Herbert Vere Evatt speaks on women's rights and how economic conditions relate to war, a delegate from France speaks on the mission of the council, Dean Virginia C. Gildersleeve on education, Emilio A. Godoy on the most important function of the council, and Alger Hiss.
  - Proceedings of Commission III, Committee 3, 1945 June 12 (Box 5)
    Presiding: Wilhelm Munthe Morgenstierne.
    Speakers: Joseph Paul-Boncour, a delegate from France, Senator Tom Connally, Grayson Kirk.
  - Proceedings of Commission III, Committee 4, 1945 June 13 (Box 5)
    V. K. Wellington Koo presents the committee's report, Senator Arthur H. Vandenberg speaks on regional arrangements and how they relate to global international cooperation, Francisco Castillo Najera, Carraciolo Parra Perez of Venezuela speaks on inter-American international arrangements, Abdel Hamid Badawi Pasha, and Joseph Paul-Boncour.
    Before the committee proceedings start, the NBC reporter describes the physical setting and comments on what is expected to take place that day.
  - Proceedings of Commission I, Committee 1, 1945 June 14 (Box 5)
    Concerns the preamble of the Charter.
    Presiding: Henri Rolin.
    Speakers: Francisco Delgado, Dean Virginia C. Gildersleeve, Nalcolm Davis, a delegate from Egypt, the Earl of Halifax, Ricardo J. Alfaro, Comm. Harold E Stassen USNR, and Hector Paysse Reyes.
  - Proceedings of Commission I, Committee 1, 1945 June 15 (Box 5)